<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MUA Games</title>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:8080/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://localhost:8080</link>
    <description>MUA Games - Made. Up. Acronym.</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 21:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>New Site</title>
      <link>http://localhost:8080/articles/new-site/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 21:59:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8080/articles/new-site/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The site finally has a new look! The old site was great, but after 7 years it
was getting a little stale and out of date. Now we have a new look, a much
better stack, and better hosting – basically an upgrade all around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old tutorials have been copied over (although they are definitely showing
their age) but most of the extra junk has been removed. For now, this means the
site will be a little sparse, especially since all the MUA time available in the
near future is going into games. Don’t fret, though - more tutorials, libraries,
and games are on the horizon (although with indefinite timelines).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, enjoy the minimal content, email us if you have anything to ask or say,
and keep making games!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Games as Art</title>
      <link>http://localhost:8080/articles/games-as-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 17:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:8080/articles/games-as-art/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As always, the “Video Games are/aren’t Art” argument is in full swing, with
Roger Ebert (seriously?) apparently as the newest celebrity to chime in. You can
read his latest rant on the subject &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/2010/04/video_games_can_never_be_art.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert frames his blathering as a critique of a speech by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kelleesantiago.com/thatgamecompany.html&quot;&gt;Kellee
Santiago&lt;/a&gt; of thatgamecompany in which she apparently says games are art, but
agrees with Ebert’s original point of “No one in or out of the field has ever
been able to cite a game worthy of comparison with the great poets, filmmakers,
novelists, and poets” (apparently he holds the poets in extra high regard,
worthy of the double mention). His most salient claim is that games are
inherently separate from art because you can win a game but you can only
experience art. He doesn’t support this with anything but applies it across
the board to chess, basketball, maj jong, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree with both Ebert and Santiago on almost every point, but everything
falls back to the definition of art, so let’s begin there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santiago goes with a Wikipedia definition (edit timestamp unknown):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Art is the process of deliberately arranging elements in a way that appeals to
the senses or emotions”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also says&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Art is a way of communicating ideas to an audience in a way that the audience
finds engaging”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert takes Plato’s definition of art as the imitation of nature, extends it to
mean improvement upon nature through the artist’s vision (he prefers art have
one artist, but concedes to himself that multi-artist pieces can still be art…
again totally unsupported), then tacks on the “art can’t be anything that can
be won” part mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure where the definition of art became so convoluted. In my opinion,
art is something that makes you think or feel. This includes &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.louvre.fr/llv/activite/detail_parcours.jsp?CONTENT%3C%3Ecnt_id=10134198674098115&amp;amp;CURRENT_LLV_PARCOURS%3C%3Ecnt_id=10134198674098115&amp;amp;bmLocale=en&quot;&gt;the masterpieces&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/images?q=cave+art&quot;&gt;cave art&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/2010/04/video_games_can_never_be_art.html&quot;&gt;4’33”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2008/mar/30/art.spain&quot;&gt;a starving dog&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Black_Square.jpg&quot;&gt;black square&lt;/a&gt;, etc, but
equally includes an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=weEb9S6YyQs&quot;&gt;impassioned speech&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ik8jICj8juc&quot;&gt;choreographed dance&lt;/a&gt;, a raked
zen rock garden, an exceptional meal, a perfectly executed pass/shot/goal/step
or a truly inspired play/move. You may not like it — in fact some art is
created specifically to enrage or offend — but that doesn’t negate its
existence as art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Staying on topic, video games can be art on many different levels. Games like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://armorgames.com/play/751/shift&quot;&gt;Shift&lt;/a&gt; turn the idea of a traditional level on its head (get it?). &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldofwarcraft.com&quot;&gt;World
of Warcraft&lt;/a&gt; can get you so attached to your digital accomplishments that
you &lt;a href=&quot;http://play.tm/news/6121/child-dies-as-parents-play-mmog-in-korea/&quot;&gt;forget about the real world&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bay12games.com/dwarves/&quot;&gt;Dwarf Fortress&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most
feature-deep games you’ll ever play juxtaposed with a minimalist interface
throwback to 1980. &lt;a href=&quot;http://kotaku.com/5350485/canabalt-the-best-one-button-game-youll-play-today&quot;&gt;Canabalt&lt;/a&gt; makes entertainment out of a single button.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tatsuya-koyama.com/software/wg002_genetos_eng.html&quot;&gt;Genetos&lt;/a&gt; is a shmup meta-commentary on shmups (I expect Ebert would be
happy as a clam with a movie full of throwbacks to all the old influential
directors and styles you suffer through in film class, but couldn’t give the
time of day to Genetos). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.infinity-universe.com/Infinity&quot;&gt;Infinity&lt;/a&gt; is a game that leverages procedural
content so thoroughly that you literally have an entire galaxy to play in.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portal_(video_game)&quot;&gt;Portal&lt;/a&gt; gets you to care about a box more than yourself;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://armorgames.com/play/2407/karoshi-suicide-salaryman&quot;&gt;Karoshi Suicide Salaryman&lt;/a&gt; does just the opposite. &lt;a href=&quot;http://towlr.com/&quot;&gt;Towlr&lt;/a&gt; is so
incredibly simple that it is maddeningly difficult. All of these push some
boundary or inspire you to think or feel something, despite most of them having
a clear way to ‘win’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert’s only criticism seems to be the win condition — he even comments about an
immersive game without points or rules (think &lt;a href=&quot;http://secondlife.com/?v=1.1&quot;&gt;Second Life&lt;/a&gt;), saying “it
ceases to be a game and becomes a representation of a story, a novel, a play,
dance, a film. Those are things you cannot win; you can only experience them”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the most inspired quote from Ebert’s article, although likely not for
the reasons he intended. He touches the important part of art that he seems to
be missing with his tunnel vision: the experience. The art of video games and
everything else is in the experience. Without context, previously formed
opinions, feelings, and memories art wouldn’t be able to carry its meaning (or
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Un_Chien_Andalou&quot;&gt;intentional lack of meaning&lt;/a&gt;). Winning, like the end of a movie, isn’t the
point – it is simply the motivation for the experience. I honestly cannot fathom
how he critiques movies without this integral piece of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ebert never makes a solid point, condemning video games as not-art because they
can be won, because he doesn’t see a reason he would like them, or because, in
his embarrassingly inexperienced opinion, they don’t compare to the masterworks
of history. None of these things have anything to do with art — medium, personal
taste, and quality simply cannot change something from being art. At every turn,
his criticisms are awkward and uninspired. The acclaim awarded him by a
passing generation, once a free pass to orate indiscriminately, now appears
more like the oxygen tank that keeps him alive but means grandpa can’t go on
the fun rides at the amusement park anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footnote:
On &lt;a href=&quot;http://thatgamecompany.com/games/flower/&quot;&gt;Flower&lt;/a&gt; Ebert says, ‘Nothing …
from this game seemed of more than decorative interest on the level of a
greeting card’. Where the hell is he buying his greeting cards?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Article image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixabay.com/en/pencils-crayons-colourful-rainbow-452238/&quot;&gt;https://pixabay.com/en/pencils-crayons-colourful-rainbow-452238/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>